so let's start the uh today lecture
today lecture is Advanced acoustic
modeling
um
so today's lecture is composed of two
items uh first one is contact dependent
hidden Markov model and second one is
adaptation
and then if we have extra time I will
also go to the language modeling section
which is a plan to be explained in the
next time but I just want to save more
time in the next other time for several
explanations about the coding assignment
and so on so hope I can try to also
start the language modeling in the
today's lecture
okay so today's lecture uh context
dependent hidden Markov model adaptation
is in the acoustic modeling part
and let me first recap uh what we have
done uh previous lectures we actually uh
dealing with the hidden Markov model
right and the hidden Markov model is
introduced to represent the acronym
representation and even phoneme can be
represented with the Father the
composition are based on the state
uh like uh in this example uh phoneme
1 2
is the composite the HM State one of the
silence beginning a second one third one
and the same for the other acronym like
a t and so on so this is the our most uh
precise unit uh introduced in our
courses however this uh unit is still
not enough to capture the variation of
the phoneme
the most famous are the opponium
variation is a context dependent on him
context to dependent hidden Market model
first I put the two
water a car and are key
can you just try to pronounce it both a
car
and Aki
and the please focus on K the consonant
k
a car
it's comments are the by other from the
the first opponing which is usually open
the mouse
and they are key
uh sorry that the the
occur is usually having the opponing uh
the uh okay other phoneme it's uh the
first pronunciated and then the AR is uh
the following and this AR is either
they're based on R and the features that
are sounded by making the mass open
a key
is uh the the followed by the vowel e
which is actually close uh compared with
r and then in this case k is actually
slightly changed acoustically a color
and a key if you also pronounce it this
2K you could actually see where you are
the how to say make a Resonance of the
phoneme K which is actually it's
slightly different depending on the
context
so actually many of the phone phonemes
changing slightly this acoustic property
depending on the context
so two other consider these are the
context dependency
we actually open further expand our Pony
unit to consider the context
for example depending on the previous
volume and the following the phoneme we
actually using the different phoneme
category
in this case
K following a
and the K following I would be
considered as a different category
this sounds very cool in terms of making
our acronym to be very precise right
however if we really consider this uh
the variations is actually quite mixed
our category a large
now for example let's say we have a 40
eponyms
and then the these 44 names depending on
the previous spawning previous 40 ponyms
and depending on the previous uh the the
following 40 pointings
so and also we have a three state about
the pony then the total number of hmm
state would be two hundred thousand
so we try to kind of capture the uh the
opponing variation with the 200 000
categories
and the what is thinking about this
number of the categories it is too big
right
um 40 manageable 120 manageable but the
uh the 200 000 is too much
and actually this is not only just the
number of funny units or two large
there will be a lot of unseen funny in
the data
so it is very difficult to cover the
variation of the old phonics in the
corpus
so instead of other using 200 000 of the
states
we actually using the clustering
and then using the phoneme that is a
kind of set of the other several other
these other state other one unit instead
of considering all context dependent
hidden Microsoft model other single
category so that we avoid to have a 200
000 other units to be like around
thousand or ten thousand and so on
and how to make this clustering is the
next the next question
and then the what we will do is actually
uh using the clustering technique
this clustering technique is called
phonetic decision tree clustering
and the two other make this kind about
clustering we actually using the top
down manner
first
phoneme
which consider all context
so this means that we don't consider the
context right this other due to node is
actually context independent form
and then let's try to make our context
dependent upon but as I said instead of
consider all possible volume state
we just try to Cluster this volume based
on some rule
often we use is a phonetic question
for example in this question cases the
following funny
is boiler or whatever
by asking this question
we can cluster
to set up the anaphonyms from the
original other single uh the context
dependent volumes
like in this case it's
this is only applied for the other
following company
so previous phoneme I didn't change
but in these cases only the phoneme that
have boiled in the other following
that is clustered as a one other unit
and the other is the best
and this other question is applied to
other other many of the uh the this
other node and try to find the best
cluster that is the first question
so for example the other question
possibly would be this phoneme is nether
or not
the preceding phoneme is neither or not
then we can have a different spirit
compared to the previous split right
and basically we make this kind of a
question
so this question can be born on a
crossbow or not front boy or not neither
or not silence or non-silence or not or
even individual other funny as a
question
uh is it a or is it e or something like
that so all these questions are made
first as a phonetic questions
and then
apply to each node
and then selecting the best spirit
based on some criteria I will explain
what kind of criteria we will use
but by doing that we can find the best
cluster
uh best are the Spirit uh in terms of
some kind of criteria
for each node right
this is just starting from the Newton
order at the context independent upon to
just splitting the two one and we using
the other the question several times to
find the best spirit
this is only just one Spirit but this
Spirit can be recursively done
for each
for each node right we first do some
other the question
and then find the best question and then
split this kind of a two node
and this is not the end of the
clustering because this is only other
splitting the other all volumes two
context independent volumes so we apply
these questions
other again here to split other their
father uh that uh the node and this kind
of split process is recursively
performed
and the finally we make a three
and then after we make a tree regarding
for example this unit
as our other data that you need this
cluster this deep node as our unit and
so on
by doing that uh we avoided to have a
two hundred thousand States
but in this case it's for example one
two three four it can be more actually
but basically uh that by using that we
can actually add a cluster the hmm state
uh efficiently based on this phonetic uh
the question
okay so uh this is the uh the the
clustering album is itself but of course
clustering requires some criteria right
I said that the score
and what score are we will use
there are a lot of by the way variety
like the most uh the the
most discriminative method would be to
use the ASR performance right
every time we spread
we compute the speech equation
performance
and then other get the best are the
uh the spirit and so on
but it is very expensive
so people usually don't do it
second approach is that we should always
care about the number of the other data
assigned to this other cluster right
as I mentioned these are the Clusters
will be the unit to avoid the over
training
so if we have a more data more kind of
our other the uh you need this means
that the more data will be assigned to
this other unit
so in this for example cases uh if we
have a more uh data unit
this means that we will avoid it will
have our uh that over training but the
two other directory measure this kind of
our other over training issue probably
number of accounts we don't have to be
the one possibility and this is actually
used in many cases
uh number of the data number of frames
assigned to this cluster
however uh this one doesn't care so much
about the acoustic other feature
information
so to uh the fully represent the
gaussian or two three represent acoustic
feature people actually using the
gaussian uh to represent this other
cluster like we represent at the hidden
Markov model itself as a gaussian okay
however here I just want to mention that
we use a single gaussian
not using the gaussian mixture model
the reason is that the gaussian mixture
model is actually making the uh the uh
the EM organ uh with the EM algorithm
that we can also compute the likelihood
of the gaussian mixture model
however this process as you can see that
we perform the question here
Spirit the uh the uh node and then
computer likelihood
we do that for all the questions and
selecting the best question and moving
to the next node and so on this actually
computation is quite heavy so every time
Computing the EM algorithm is quite
difficult
so instead we actually using the single
gaussian and we even using the picture
element
not other moving the HTML state
so other in these cases we actually just
make some initial model
and then performing the other alignment
and the fixed alignment and then
complete the gaussian
so by using that other if we fix the
alignment we can actually avoid to have
the EM iterative computation and we can
compute the likelihood either one shot
based on uh the uh for this other all of
the variations
so this is the clip of making this
clustering to be unattractable based on
a small computation
so I will explain a bit more about these
other algorithms but it's a little bit
uh High uh it's a little bit an advanced
topic so uh the in addition to this
lecture please also check the difference
that I put in this slide
anyway I will try to explain about the
algorithm
so first
to compute this uh the uh
single gaussian likelihood
We performed a bit of algorithm for all
the data and get the HTML State sequence
by the way you guys may think why uh we
started using the beta vehicle system
which means that we already have a model
right
yes we are assuming that we have a model
so for this kind of hmm based approaches
we always assuming we have some initial
model
and then getting the beta arrive and
then doing this processing and so on and
after we get each unit we actually
performing the hmm GMM biomerate
algorithm again
so this other process is actually at the
work the having the biology algorithm in
everywhere
and once we compute the alignment of all
the kind of other data and the
corresponding are the hmm state
we could actually compute the gaussian
statistics the sufficient statistics
that I mentioned before
and then based on this other gaussian
statistics
we can actually compute a diagram
I will omit that all the kind of
derivation but please check this uh the
final equation
this is the likelihood of each node
this likelihood is computed by the old
account number of the frames
assigned to this node
and then other final part
this D is a dimension
so only that we care about this part and
this is actually variance parameter
and this variance is not for the other
single hmm state but we consider the all
clustering or the kind of uh the hmm
state in a cluster
and then compute the variance
and this actually can be the efficiently
performed if we already know the
gaussian statistics so this actually
computation does not require the
iterative process
and then we compute this other variance
and then making this other likelihood
value
so this is I will say one shot
we don't need an em algorithm we don't
need a other the port of acquired or
beta by algorithm and so on we need a
beta algorithm once but that's another
one time is fine
and then other which when we get the
likelihood of this other the each node
this one
we actually compute the like logarithm
difference
this is also completed by uh these are
the equation which is actually the
likelihood term
yes spirit
no spirit
minus previous uh the unspirited node
so this first term is corresponding to
the
likelihood of this one
okay
and the
this
uh the likelihood
corresponding to the likelihood here
and then the last Saturday of the
likelihood
corresponding to the unspirited node
okay
so that if we change for example
questions
at least this value can be changed based
on this equation
and then by using this uh the like log
likelihood as a Criterion we can
actually find the maximum split uh from
the or possible other question uh in the
node
so the again the answer is we're just
using the directory field
single gaussian based and then we can
actually compute it efficiently
um any other questions any questions
about this product
yes
I is the hmm State one of the HM State
before clustering
included in the older kind of uh the
node Omega okay
foreign
I'll say that this part is little bit
complicated
and this part is a little bit advanced
and this part is little two Advanced to
be listed in the midterm exam
I gave you one hint yeah this this part
is very important and I'd like you to
understand this one but first understand
the concept and then check the reference
paper and so on yeah
yes
the data the number of the account yeah
so the in the uh included in each node
number of the frames
okay uh
any other high level questions about
this one
can people understand anyway we have our
have to consider the context
in the HTML standard States
but it is too many
so we have to classize
and then we want to use usually using
the gaussian statistics
to find the best permutation based
against the other Spirit other of the
hmm state
and this unit is the uh the standard
unit
used for the real hmm based system
so this is actually very complicated but
it is quite widely used
okay then the uh the
um
I just explained that
the
uh we use a maximum likelihood criteria
to select the
uh appropriate question for each
for each node right by applying this
kind of a maximum right period of
criteria we can get the optimum speed
for each of the node right
however
I didn't actually explain about the
important things
or the clustering the other important
part is
how to set the number of clusters
right
and let me check whether what is my
question for this
okay
[Music]
um
maybe I can ask the question now
uh can you uh
make the question to be enabled
[Music]
the question is about
uh we can only use the maximum
likelihood criteria
Criterion to make a decision tree
yes yes
one more minute
yes
foreign
[Music]
okay I'll finish the uh Paul
so what do you have asking what exactly
very good questions
if for example we applied a question
what is the equation to every time for
me to know
and then maximum Library
always increase the title of the body
and then their answer is try to split
all that kind of ignore as many as
possible
and which can be equal to hundred
thousand that I mentioned so sometimes
questions also include in the immediate
individual opponing like this other
point is a or not that's a problem so as
long as we have certain questions
foreign
so this doesn't have any meanings right
our other intention is to control
the other sufficient numbers of clusters
so maximum likelihood is
not the best criteria
uh for this other purpose it is good for
the selecting the best question for each
node
but it doesn't either be used as an
entire clustering measure
and then actually some people are using
the several other model selection
criteria
like a minimum description like this or
based on information criteria or
operational base and so on
uh by the way uh the my first other
paper my first research in speech is
using the parational base for this
phonetic decision clustering
and then try to find the optimal
structure
in terms of the Bayesian criteria
and this is actually the advanced topics
again
and if people are using developing a
various techniques to find the other
what is the kind of best
stop criteria for this
uh the clustering problem
and the other method is a little bit
heuristics
but let's say you know adjust setting
with other five thousand or ten thousand
uh making a more I got this one with the
other hook other heuristic parameters
to decide the size
and some other people also using the
threshold or setting the threshold of
this kind of other uh logo algorithm
difference if this look like refute the
difference becomes smaller than some
threshold we also split the uh the uh
the northern and so on so there are a
lot of ways to control uh this uh the
number of clusters
and the currently many people actually
just using the set of Maximum Recon
order
but again a lot of systems are using
different ways
so let's uh the the view this entire
algorithm
I mentioned the other couple of times
before but I just summarize it
first are the uh
make a context independent
hidden Markov model
so in the beginning we performing the
hmm GMM
but using the context independent one
why we need this one
with this kind of initial model
we can perform the betaab algorithm to
get the alignment of the old data in
terms of the hmm
and then fix this other alignment and
then creating the statistics and so on
given the alignment we know that other
how many hmm how many frames are
assigned to the hmm state right the
answer about the question 450 is again
the number of frame assigned in this
beta B step after the B type step we
know that all the data belongs to
feature hmm state so we can compute the
number of them for each agenda State and
even other values like a mean and
variance and so on
and then other performing the three this
uh the the political condition to the
clustering
to get the added a context dependent
other unit
and then we're performing the hmm at GMM
again training again
so we at least need to have two em
algorithm two other bombers algorithms
to get the final uh the hmm GMM state if
are using the context-dependent acoustic
models
and this part are that is again now
replaced with a deep neural network
especially this GMM part this GMM path
is depressed to be the Deep neural
network
but still the other the hmm based deep
in your network is following this kind
of other approaches
so are the priests are the also uh the
understand
that uh this kind of a framework
and then the other what kind of uh the
haramic hyper parameter becomes
important in the hmm State uh in the hmm
GMM
as I mentioned previously in the ahm
gaussian mixture model I said that the
number of gaussian
are important hyper parameters
but now we also hover uh the the hmm
States number of context dependent HMS
data is also very important hyper
parameter
so if we usually uh the the the the
specify the uh the uh hidden Markov
model GMM for Speed definition we
usually use these two hyper parameters
now Bob at the total hmm State and the
number of uh that are the total
gaussians
and then specify the model
that is what we usually do uh for the
other specifying the hmm base speed
definition
and again even we move this one to the
Deep neural network systems and this
part will be replaced with a different
neural network but this part is not the
place in the Deep neural network so
these are the the hyper parameter is
still important for other hmm deep
neural network a base speed definition
okay so this is about the uh
the uh the context dependent hidden
locomotor yes
correct yes
we don't do it which is very expensive
so are they uh we don't do it instead
that we fix alignment and then we're
using the finger gaussian and then we
don't have to do the EM algorithm
anymore so this is a very important uh
understanding uh we doing the other the
WWE alignment
but during the uh phonetic decision
crafting we don't do any other VW
element code as you see beta development
is expensive right we have to check can
each data
and we actually can get the statistics
so I also explained about sufficient
statistics
with this strategy and the statistics we
don't have to scan the data anymore but
we can either compute all the likelihood
of each node
yeah very good question and this is
again the important concept by the way
this sounds very rather large
approximations right but practice
practically if it's working
okay uh let's uh move to the next agenda
uh this is the adaptation
and still I am talking about the the uh
uh acoustic modeling part
and then are talking about the
adaptation
I've grown this one
so not only for speech recognition
problems in general if we using the data
always that data has bias right
and then uh if we have a new data
we have to adapt our model to that
specific environment
that adaptation technique is very very
popular
in many of the machine learning problems
and of course other essential in speech
recognition
and in spiritual condition historically
uh adaptation techniques was either the
the most investigated or speaker
so if for example other may we make a
speaker
Independence speech equal instance
systems by correcting many of your
voices
that will be good in terms of the
collecting many data and in terms of
making the system to be robust to be a
speaker right
however
if we have some particular persons about
the data that is available and then we
could adapt to the model from this other
speaker independent model to the speaker
dependent system right
so this is a very well-known uh
adaptation uh the techniques are used in
the speech recognition and the two other
data is this other speaker adaptation uh
there are two types of the approach
one of the maximum of posterior
adaptation and the data is maximum
linear likelihood linear regression ml
allow adaptation
by the way can you guys come up with the
other adaptation done speaker
speech has a lot of variations right yes
accent is very good yes
any other
variations that we could
anything else
gender yes but it's a kind of a similar
to that speaker right
you can also have devices device yeah
getting similar to what I want yeah
um the right thing that are more like on
their body their environment right and
the other important reporting
environment is provided by Northeast
this is very very important for me so
other these adaptation techniques can
also be used for the noise devapiration
condition by the way not only for the
speaker but all the other the what you
guys mentioned the accent at the agenda
are the sentiments and so on are very
good point yeah this is actually uh the
the importance for speech equation to be
adapted to such kind of environment
by the way people may think about
language it would be another possibility
right this is completely true
however uh in a conflict modeling
adaptation uh
need a
theoretically grounded part industry
performed in this next curve and the
language important part right and the
theoretically acoustic modeling is
can be our language independent given
the speech features to predicting the
form right or pointing Point
implications a little bit gravity
dependent but if we try to put it along
the form IPA formed and so on this is
language independent right
but practically actually the uh language
dependency exists in the acoustic model
and also other language uh the
adaptation is also used in the
acoustical modeling part
but the people mostly focused on the
noise and the
um
noise and the the speaker in the
acoustic modeling context
okay let's first talk about the maximum
posterior estimation
this is actually already appeared in our
course
for example to solving this PW given o
we actually add a decompose it to the
likelihood
and the PW this is a player
and then other using the other this
optimization instead instead of this one
is the mostly people are called as a
maximum Apostolic a parameter estimation
so uh this is the uh the case uh the
that we asked the predicting the speech
recognition transcript
but let's move to this discussion in the
parameter estimation
so in the parameters estimation we have
discussed a lot for the maximum
likelihood base estimation right
basically uh we either try to solve the
uh the parameters based on this criteria
although this is a little bit difficult
in the hmm GMM cases so we're using the
EM algorithm and so on but anyway
basically a maximum likelihood
estimation is try to estimate the uh the
the parameter of this diaculated value
however in the maximum opportunity
estimation it is actually regarding the
likelihood value and are the
uh prior distribution like similar to
the other we either consider the
language model as a player
and then did we either using this uh the
equation fuse solve uh the uh parameters
Vision instead of only consider the
likelihood
so the difference is whether prior
distribution is included or not
so by the way this is the the one of the
approximation of the Bayesian method
and the other more strict Bayesian
method usually also the marginalize
these parameters and this is you know
mostly done by the variational base
Monte Carlo uh and so on but again in
this lecture uh these are more advanced
topics so we more focus on the maximum
library with a sorry maximum of
posteriority estimation by only
constelling a prior information other
additional other function in the
optimization process
okay so now the uh we have this kind of
factors and then let's talk about what
is the difference
so uh say that we try to kind of uh
estimate the uh the ideal uh likely
ideal other parameters gaussian
parameters and so on
and the other
we have for example
uh that this kind of a true distribution
here
okay
however
in some cases
we only get the buyer sample here
okay
this this is just a buyer sample if we
have more samples probably we can get
the uh this distribution at this sample
to be similar to this true distribution
but the due to that issue in the uh the
uh decoding or whatever we only have
some selected portion of the point
and then what happens when we do the
maximum likelihood
we just try to uh the the estimate the
uh the parameter which just fit to this
uh data right
however
if
we know some prior distribution for
example this data tends to go to the
left side
in some cases we know the prior
distribution speech cases it's more
naturally we can get a prior information
because it's a physical other problem so
we can actually find some prior
constraints but anyway if we have this
prior constraint and then this actual
data we could actually possibly recover
this through distribution
although the other difficulty is how to
get supplier information right
and then again going back to the speak
adaptation phase it
so as I mentioned in the speaker
adaptation
we first
build speech recognition system by
correcting many speakers
and then making a speaker independent
system
why we collect many speakers
because it is very difficult to collect
enough amount of training data from
single speaker right
so instead we ask you guys to speak
uh five minutes and then we can easily
get you know 250 minutes of the data
right instead of one person here to
speak the four hours it is very
efficient way to collect the data right
and then we have this kind of speaker
independent system
yes this is a speaker independent system
so it's slightly different
from the uh the uh the other other
Target speaker like my voice and the
speaker independent system May is
definitely different however it is not
very different right Aura come from the
humans voices
and actually some of the the voices are
that of your
voice can be actually close to mine
right so this speaker independent model
can be a very good prior distribution
speaker dependent system so this is very
reasonable assumption so this actually
approach is widely used added for uh the
speaker adaptation setup
so we can do the same analogy to even
accent or a noise or sentiment or
whatever we first collect many data as
much as possible and then using with the
supplier model and then adapting to the
other other Target other attribute that
is other the methodology that the the
prior based approach is working
foreign
estimation
we can actually follow the exactly same
process as the uh the agent parameter
estimation
so this part the uh dearly we have too
many uh the equations
so I'm mostly skipping it and I also
that adding the difference so please
check this one and again I will try to
explain uh there are some high level
Concepts rather than explain the detail
for this other explanation about it
um the anyway the the
the procedure is almost same uh using
the uh introducing dating the variable
and making a complete data likelihood
making the organization function and the
parameter estimation then the solvon
and the uh later in the variable
introduction is actually exactly the
same we're just using the hmm State and
the other the gaussian mixture
so we skip this one
and the complete data likelihood is
changed since we also try to consider
this seater
as an incomplete data and then we making
the joint probability of the observation
State sequence uh the gaussian mixture
sequence and the parameter so it becomes
actually very complicated but again
other please you do not have to entirely
follow this equation I just want to
mention that the uh the we need to
consider this filter to make
the other
good
after that aux Theory function is also
defined
however this ogre function is actually
uh just formed at the original auxiliary
function
and the prior distribution
so we can actually compute this one at
the efficiently by using the same uh the
portable quad algorithm
but just see the some modification of
this other data prior distribution part
and the parameter estimation uh and so
on
this is also almost same except that we
have some kind of additional prior
distribution function
and the I
that the the most of the question I had
for this kind of Prior distribution is
that what kind of distribution we should
set
and then the other like uh the the we
have discussed in the previous uh hmm
based uh the the distribution setup uh
prior distribution setup is also uh
easily uh they provided by following the
rule
first we should consider the domain of
the parameters
uh for actually rate parameters relating
the initial weight the the mixture away
and the uh the state transition uh this
is actually the the uh the the sun has
to satisfy the sample and condition
and these are the parameters are model
divided judicial distribution
okay the next question
uh the
gaussian parameters
uh should we add uh which kind of
distribution should we use to uh the
represent a gaussian mean parameters
actually it's already written here
the answer is the gaussian right
the reason is because gaussian mean is
not bounded
same for the mscc features
so we should actually using the other
gaussian distribution
however the issue is the body and
parameters
this is bounded
so at the prior distribution we use the
gamma distribution
so these are kind of the exercises that
you guys should remember are not other
for this kind of only for this other map
estimation in general
uh that if we try to provide in the
actual distribution you have to consider
the domain of the parameters and then
either providing the appropriate
distribution
however one another constraint is that
these distribution must be an
exponential family otherwise we cannot
get the cross pump solution
so actually we don't have so many
options just the gaussian gamma we shot
a delicious
limited other options
okay so by doing that uh we set the the
prior distributions
uh based on the uh did Issue rate
distribution here
and the normal distribution and the
gamma distribution
each of the kind of a prior distribution
is added becomes the uh is the
representing the domain of the each
parameter like a pi a w mu and the r
and these are are the the further
parameterized by the other uh the the
parameters and these parameters of the
parameters are called hyper parameters
in the Bayesian context
and again that this part I will mostly
skip it because it is very complicated
but uh just I want to show you the one
of the solution
this is the solution of the mean
parameter based on the map estimation
if you do not care about this one it is
just removing this one
um only with this
uh solution
do you remember is this the what is the
the result of this estimation yes this
is exactly maximum likelihood estimation
right
and then actually the map estimation
have a additional time here
and I will explain about this additional
term here by the way this mu zero
corresponding to the prior distribution
so this one is again the the sum of the
mean parameters estimated from the
speaker independent models and then this
one is corresponding to the speaker
adaptation data
okay uh let's move to understand this
kind of a solution
for example
if
we don't have any data
what happened if we don't have any
adaptation data what's happened
this means that this
this other data goes to zero right
and then only we consider this term
and then this data denominator and the
numerator is canceled
so if there is no data it goes to the
speaker independent model parameters
but it makes sense right if there is no
data we're just using a speaker
independent models
okay let's consider the opposite cases
if we have too many adaptation data of
my voice
what's happening
this data becomes too dominant and then
this one we can actually ignore it right
and then this solution becomes maximum
likelihood of my voice
so again this one is correcting from all
of you guys data and then making a
speech equation system which is very
valid if we don't have any amount of my
voice
right
but if we have too many uh the enough
sufficient amount of my data
we should use the maximum likelihood
estimation of my data right
and then multiple estimation is actually
the uh represented other
uh the interpolation of this point
and depending on the amount of data the
estimation of the parameters goes from
here to gradually goes to the maximum
regular destination
so very theoretically beautiful solution
we can get
so this is actually the other well-known
map adaptation of other performance
this is the amount of the adaptation
training data again my voice
and this is the accuracy
of speech recognition performance so
higher is better
let's say maximum likelihood performance
the beginning we don't cover my voice so
we cannot make a model right but
gradually we have a data we can make a
speech equation system of my voice
other with enough amount of data this is
the more like uh the
the straight word uh the the
performance curve I would say and then
map adaptation is actually starting from
the speaker Independence part
and then in the smaller amount of
training data mapped with actually
getting a better performance especially
you know this kind of uh the irregular
area
uh this is very true that based on this
equation
we at least added The Preserve that this
system can provide a speaker independent
model performance so it does not go to
zero
and then theoretically if we have a
large amount of data
maximum likelihood maximum posteriorly
are the adaptation is equivalent to the
maximum likelihood of performance
so that's the kind of map estimation and
the map adaptation
and the I will quickly explain about the
other estimation method and then we'll
finish my lecture
the other estimation approach maximum
likelihood linear regression is also
widely used as an alternative field map
estimation
this approach
is basically uh try to
find the transformation of the gaussian
parameters
so as I mentioned that the gaussian
parameter is like a 10 000 to 100
000 depending on the system
it's so many
so that we require that the significant
amount of data to train the model
however instead of playing this model
let's try to find the uh the the the
transformation that is a limited or
adaptation
so for example if we have this kind of
other barriers
uh the gaussian model
and then maximum likelihood estimation
is to find this kind of mean variance
and so on for each parameters
but instead of finding this kind about
each parameter
uh this uh ml error is try to find the
linear regression
of all discussion parameters
so if you check this kind of added
equations
you can see that J K again corresponding
to the hmm State and the gaussian
mixture so total a number of gaussians
would be like a 10 000 and so on
however
instead of estimating this one we only
estimating this one
so this is just a linear Matrix
so the number of parameters is very
small
even we have a millions of the gaussians
this other parameter is like order of
the hundred or a thousand only that a
small number of parameters to find the
transformation
so by doing that uh since number of the
other parameters becomes very small
we can actually estimate this uh the the
parameters efficiently
and there are a lot of variants of this
kind of approaches for example instead
of estimating the other transformation
of the other parameters
we can also consider the transformation
of the speech feature itself this is by
the almost equivalent solution
but anyway the important point is that
this estimation or this estimation is
solved by the EM algorithm
similar to the map adaptation by using
this other parametric form we can
estimate these other parameters based on
the EM algorithm
and I'm it sounds like I'm they're
saying very terrible things but you guys
may also think why not using the
non-linear function
why not using a more complicated
transformation but still at a small
number of parameters can we do that the
answer is no
uh we cannot actually solve the equation
so this linear constant is one of the
only constraints that we can get the EM
a based solution
so uh this approach and the map approach
is very unique in the sense that we can
get the EMR voice-based solution and the
other parametric approach basically
cannot get the solution based on the EM
so it is very inefficient
and the uh I will finally explain about
the
uh the these three adaptation
technique
so as I mentioned the maximum likelihood
that the map has this kind of behavior
and the emerald is actually located in
this kind of the region
in the ml estimation the number of
parameters is just a transformation
parameters very small
so it's working only with a very small
amount of data so it's actually the
getting the other
uh the better performance in the
beginning of the amount of training data
however
do you think this transformation is
enough accurate
to uh convert all the kind of gaussian
to be the uh the the
desired form
the answer is no
this is only linear transformation right
so compared with maximum likelihood or
map estimation these are the
representation is very weak too much
confident to get to the accurate
performance when we have the large
amount of training data
so of course there are a lot of
techniques to make the ml
performed better in this region but by
using the simple material we actually
have this kind of issue that the if the
amount of print data is that it doesn't
reach to the map or a maximum right
estimation
but again there are a lot of ways to
sort of disapproach this and one of them
is actually this paper
solving the problem of this region based
on the digression tree
and the let's go to the uh short short
quiz
uh second one
maybe the this one with this graph it is
obvious but uh please answer it
thank you
30 more seconds
okay please close the poll
so the answer is uh ever made at all
right since the number of parameters are
very small so it's actually quickly
adopted uh to the Target or the the
speaker performance and so on
okay so I wanted to move to the language
modeling but it's almost uh the the time
to finish so I would like to uh accept
questions
any questions